Last year when I was here, I was speaking to you about a swim
العام الماضي عندما كنت هنا، كنت أتحدث عن السباحة
which I did across the North Pole.
التي أنجزتها بقطع القطب الشمالي.
And while that swim took place three years ago,
وبينما تلك السباحة قد حدثت قبل ثلاث أعوام مضت،
I can remember it as if it was yesterday.
يمكن أن أتذكرها كما لو كانت بالأمس.
I remember standing on the edge of the ice,
أذكر وقوفي على حافة الجليد،
about to dive into the water,
وقد أقتربت من القفز إلى المياه،
and thinking to myself, I have never ever
وأفكر بيني وبين نفسي، لم أرى قط
seen any place on this earth
مكان على هذه الأرض
which is just so frightening.
مرعب بهذا القدر.
The water is completely black.
لقد كانت المياة داكنة كلياً.
The water is minus 1.7 degrees centigrade,
وكانت درجة حرارة المياة ناقص 1.7 درجة مئوية
or 29 degrees Fahrenheit.
أو 29 درجة فهرنهايت.
It's flipping freezing in that water.
إنه تجميد كلي في تلك المياة.
And then a thought came across my mind:
ثم جاء خاطر على ذهني:
if things go pear-shaped on this swim,
إذا لم تسر الأمور بشكل جيد أثناء السباحة،
how long will it take for my frozen body
كم من الزمن سيستغرق جسدي المجمد
to sink the four and a half kilometers
ليقطع أربعة كيلومترات ونصف
to the bottom of the ocean?
ليصل لقاع المحيط؟
And then I said to myself, I've just got to get this thought
ثم قلت لنفسي، ينبغي أن أتخلص من هذه الفكرة
out of my mind as quickly as possible.
أخرجها من عقلي بأسرع ما يمكن.
And the only way I can dive
والطريقة الوحيدة التي باستطاعتي الغطس من خلالها
into that freezing cold water
في تلك المياة المتجمدة
and swim a kilometer
وقطع مسافة كيلومتر
is by listening to my iPod and really revving myself up,
تأتي عبر الإستماع إلى جهاز الآي بود وتسريع نفسي،
listening to everything from beautiful opera
الإستماع لأي شئ من الأوبرا الجميلة
all the way across to Puff Daddy,
وكل شئ حتى لموسيقى المطرب باف دادي،
and then committing myself a hundred percent --
ثم إلزام نفسي مائة بالمائة --
there is nothing more powerful than the made-up mind --
ليس هناك شئ أكثر قوة من تصميم العقل --
and then walking up to the edge of the ice
ثم المشي إلى حافة الجليد
and just diving into the water.
ثم القفز إلى المياة.
And that swim took me
وتلك السباحة أخذت مني
18 minutes and 50 seconds,
18 دقيقة و 50 ثانية،
and it felt like 18 days.
وقد خلتها مثل 18 يوماً.
And I remember getting out of the water
وأنني أذكر عند الخروج من الماء
and my hands feeling so painful
وأشعر بيدي تؤلماني جداً
and looking down at my fingers,
وأنظر إلى أصابعي
and my fingers were literally the size of sausages
وقد بدت أصابعي بحجم السجق، حرفياً
because -- you know, we're made partially of water --
لأنه كما تعلمون، نحن مخلوقون جزئياً من الماء
when water freezes it expands,
وعندما يتجمد الماء يتمدد
and so the cells in my fingers
ولذا فقد تجمدت خلايا أصابعي
had frozen and expanded
ثم تمددت
and burst.
وطفحت.
And the most immediate thought when I came out of that water
وقد كان أول شئ خطر على بالي عند الخروج من الماء
was the following:
هو التالي:
I'm never, ever
لن أذهب مطلقاً
going to do another cold water swim
للسباحة مرة أخرى في مياة باردة
in my life again.
طوال حياتي.
Anyway, last year, I heard about the Himalayas
على أي حال، سمعت في العام الماضي عن جبال الهمالايا
and the melting of the -- (Laughter)
وذوبان الجليد -- (ضحك)
and the melting of the glaciers
وذوبان الأنهار الجليدية
because of climate change.
بفعل تغير المناخ.
I heard about this lake, Lake Imja.
سمعت بهذه البحيرة، بحيرة إيمجا.
This lake has been formed in the last couple of years
وقد تشكلت البحيرة خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية
because of the melting of the glacier.
بسبب ذوبان الأنهار الجليدية.
The glacier's gone all the way up the mountain
وقد عبرت الأنهار الجليدية كل المسافة عبر الجبل
and left in its place this big lake.
وقد خلفت هذه البحيرة الكبيرة.
And I firmly believe
وأنا أعتقد جازماً
that what we're seeing in the Himalayas
أن ما نراه في جبال الهمالايا
is the next great, big battleground
هو المعركة العظيمة القادمة
on this earth.
على كوكب الأرض.
Nearly two billion people --
قرابة المليارين نسمة --
so one in three people on this earth --
واحد من كل ثلاثة أشخاص على كوكب الأرض
rely on the water from the Himalayas.
يعتمدون على المياة من الهمالايا.
And with a population increasing as quickly as it is,
ومع إزدياد سكان الأرض بوتيرة سريعة،
and with the water supply from these glaciers --
ومع تناقص إمدادات المياة من هذه الأنهار المتجمدة--
because of climate change --
بفعل تغير المناخ
decreasing so much,
تتناقص بشدة،
I think we have a real risk of instability.
أعتقد أن لدينا مخاطر عدم الإستقرار
North, you've got China; south, you've India, Pakistan, Bangladesh,
شمالاً، لدينا الصين. جنوباً، لدينا الهند، باكستان، بنغلاديش،
all these countries.
كل هذه الدول.
And so I decided
لذا فقد قررت
to walk up to Mt. Everest,
الذهاب لجبل آيفرست،
the highest mountain on this earth,
أعلى جبل على كوكب الأرض،
and go and do a symbolic swim
وأن أقوم بسباحة رمزية
underneath the summit
في القمة
of Mt. Everest.
قمة جبل آيفرست.
Now, I don't know if any of you have had the opportunity to go to Mt. Everest,
الآن، لا أعلم إن أتيحت الفرصة لأي منكم بالذهاب لجبل آيفرست،
but it's quite an ordeal getting up there.
لكنها محنة بالفعل الذهاب إلى هناك.
28 great, big, powerful yaks
28 حيوان ياك كبير وقوي
carrying all the equipment up onto this mountain --
يحملون الأمتعة لأعلى الجبل--
I don't just have my Speedo,
لا أحمل ردائي للسباحة فقط
but there's a big film crew who then
لكن هناك فريق كبير للتصوير الذي كان
send all the images around the world.
يرسل الصور لكل العالم حينئذ
The other thing which was so challenging about this swim
الشئ الآخر الذي كان معوقاً حول هذه السباحة
is not just the altitude.
ليس فقط الإرتفاع
I wanted to do the swim at 5,300 meters above sea level.
لقد اردت السباحة على علو 5300 متراً فوق مستوى سطح البحر
So it's right up in the heavens.
لذا فقد كانت كما في السماوات
It's very, very difficult to breath. You get altitude sickness.
من الصعب جداً جداً التنفس. تصاب بإعياء الإرتفاع.
I feels like you've got a man standing behind you with a hammer
وتشعر كما لو أن هناك شخص خلفك يحمل مطرقة
just hitting your head all the time.
ويضربك على رأسك طوال الوقت
That's not the worst part of it.
لم يكن هذا أسوء ما في الأمر
The worst part was this year was the year where they decided
أسوأ شئ كان، أنهم قد قرروا هذه السنة
to do a big cleanup operation on Mt. Everest.
إجراء تنظيف كبير على جبل آيفرست
Many, many people have died on Mt. Everest,
لقد مات الكثير من الناس على قمة جبل آيفرست،
and this was the year they decided to go
وقد قرروا أن يستعيدوا
and recover all the bodies of the mountaineers
كل جثث متسلقي الجبال
and then bring them down the mountain.
وجلبهم لأسفل الجبل.
And when you're walking up the mountain
وبينما أنت تسير لأعلى الجبل
to attempt to do something
لمحاولة فعل شئ
which no human has ever done before, and, in fact, no fish --
لم يفعله أي بشري على الإطلاق، وفي الحقيقة لم تفعله سمكة.
there are no fish up there swimming at 5,300 meters --
لا توجد سمكة سبحت على إرتفاع 5300 متراً.
When you're trying to do that,
بينما تحاول فعل ذلك،
and then the bodies are coming past you,
في نفس الوقت تمر بك الجثث،
it humbles you,
فذلك يضعفك
and you also realize very, very clearly
ويجعلك تدرك بصورة جلية
that nature is so much more powerful
بأن الطبيعة أقوى منا
than we are.
أكثر
And we walked up this pathway,
وقد سرنا لأعلى عبر هذا المسار
all the way up.
طوال الطريق.
And to the right hand side of us
وعلى الجانب الأيمن لنا
was this great Khumbu Glacier.
كانت أنهار خومبو المتجمدة العظيمة.
And all the way along the glacier we saw
وطوال مسار الأنهار المتجمدة رأينا
these big pools of melting ice.
هذه الأحواض الضخمة للجليد المتجمد.
And then we got up to this small lake
ثم وصلنا لهذه البحيرة الصغيرة
underneath the summit of Mt. Everest,
قبل قمة جبل آيفرست
and I prepared myself
وقد جهزت نفسي
the same way as I've always prepared myself,
بنفس الطريقة التي أجهز بها نفسي دائماً
for this swim which was going to be so very difficult.
لهذه السباحة التي ستصبح صعبة للغاية
I put on my iPod, I listened to some music,
وضعت جهاز الآي بود خاصتي، واستمعت لبعض الموسيقى
I got myself as aggressive as possible --
جعلت نفسي عدواني بأقصى ما أستطيع
but controlled aggression --
لكن عدوانية متحكم بها
and then I hurled myself
ثم ألقيت بنفسي
into that water.
في الماء
I swam as quickly as I could
سبحت بأسرع ما أستطيع
for the first hundred meters,
لأول مائة متر
and then I realized very, very quickly,
ثم أدركت بسرعة جداً
I had a huge problem on my hands.
أن لديّ مشكلة كبيرة في يديّ
I could barely breathe.
كنت أستطيع التنفس بالكاد
I was gasping for air.
كنت ألهث من أجل الهواء
I then began to choke,
ثم بدأت أختنق
and then it quickly led to me vomiting in the water.
ثم جعلني ذلك بسرعة أتقيأ في الماء
And it all happened so quickly:
وحدث كل ذلك بسرعة جداً
I then -- I don't know how it happened -- but I went underwater.
ثم -- لا أعلم مالذي حدث -- لكني ذهبت لأسفل
And luckily, the water was quite shallow,
ولحسن الحظ، كانت المياة ضحلة نسبياً
and I was able to push myself off the bottom of the lake
وقدرت على دفع نفسي إلى سطح البحيرة
and get up and then take another gasp of air.
والإستيقاظ وأخذ نفس آخر من الهواء
And then I said, carry on. Carry on. Carry on.
ثم قلت في نفسي، واصل، واصل
I carried on for another five or six strokes,
واصلت لخمس أو ست ضربات أخريات
and then I had nothing in my body,
ثم لم يبق شئ في جسمي
and I went down to the bottom of the lake.
ذهبت لأسفل البحيرة
And I don't where I got it from,
ولا أعلم من أين حصلت على ذلك
but I was able to somehow
لكني قدرت بصورة ما
pull myself up and as quickly as possible
بسحب نفسي بأسرع ما يمكن
get to the side of the lake.
والوصول للجانب الآخر من البحيرة
I've heard it said that drowning
لقد سمعت من قبل أن الغرق
is the most peaceful death that you can have.
هو أكثر الطرق السلمية تحصل بها على الموت
I have never, ever heard
ولكني لم أسمع قط
such utter bollocks.
بمثل خوار الثيران هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is the most frightening and panicky feeling
أنه أكبر شعور بالخوف والذعر
that you can have.
يمكن أن يصيبك
I got myself to the side of the lake.
أوصلت نفسي لجانب من البحيرة
My crew grabbed me,
سحبني فريق العمل
and then we walked as quickly as we could
ثم مشينا بأسرع ما يمكننا
down -- over the rubble --
أسفل -- فوق الحصى--
down to our camp.
أسفل إلى المخيم
And there, we sat down,
وهناك، جلسنا
and we did a debrief about what had gone wrong
أسترجعنا بسرعة ما حصل بصورة خاطئة
there on Mt. Everest.
هناك على جبل آيفرست
And my team just gave it to me straight.
وقد قالها لي أعضاء الفريق مباشرة
They said, Lewis, you need to have
لقد قالوا، لويس، ينبغي أن تغيّر
a radical tactical shift
تكتيكك بصورة جذرية
if you want to do this swim.
إذا أردت النجاح في هذه السباحة
Every single thing which you have learned
أي شئ قد تعلمته
in the past 23 years of swimming,
خلال ال 23 عاماً من السباحة،
you must forget.
ينبغي أن تنساها.
Every single thing which you learned
كل شئ تعلمته
when you were serving in the British army,
عندما كنت تخدم في الجيش الإنجليزي
about speed and aggression,
حول السرعة والعناد،
you put that to one side.
ينبغي أن تضع ذلك جانباً
We want you to walk up the hill in another two days' time.
نريدك أن تمضي إلى الجبل خلال يومين
Take some time to rest and think about things.
خذ بعض الوقت للراحة والتفكير حول الأشياء
We want you to walk up the mountain in two days' time,
نريدك أن تسير إلى الجبل خلال يومين
and instead of swimming fast,
وعوضاً عن السباحة بسرعة
swim as slowly as possible.
أسبح بهدوء قدر ما تستطيع
Instead of swimming crawl, swim breaststroke.
بدلاً من السباحة زحفاً، أسبح فراشة.
And remember, never ever swim with aggression.
وتذكر، لا تسبح مطلقاً بعدوانية.
This is the time to swim
هذا هو الوقت لتسبح
with real humility.
بتواضع حقيقي
And so we walked back up
وعليه صعدنا لأعلى مجدداً
to the mountain two days later.
إلى الجبل بعد يومين
And I stood there
ووقفت هناك
on the edge of the lake,
على حافة البحيرة
and I looked up at Mt. Everest --
ونظرت إلى جبل آيفرست--
and she is one of the most beautiful mountains on the earth --
وهو أحد أجمل الجبال على الأرض --
and I said to myself, just do this slowly.
وقلت لنفسي، لأفعلها بهدوء هذه المرة
And I swam across the lake.
وقد سبحت عبر البحيرة
And I can't begin to tell you
ولا أستطيع البدء باخباركم
how good I felt
كم كان شعوري جيداً
when I came to the other side.
عندما وصلت إلى الضفة الأخرى
But I learned two very, very
لكني تعلمت درسين
important lessons there on Mt. Everest,
غاية في الأهمية هناك في جبل آيفرست
and I thank my team of Sherpas who taught me this.
وأنا أشكر زملائي من فريق الشيربا الذين علموني هذا
The first one is
الدرس الأول هو
that just because something has worked in the past so well,
لأن شئ ما قد نجح في الماضي بصورة جيدة،
doesn't mean it's going to work in the future.
لا يعني أنه سينجح مجدداً في المستقبل
And similarly,
وبالمثل،
now, before I do anything,
الآن قبل أن أفعل أي شئ
I ask myself what type of mindset
سألت نفسي ما هي العقلية
do I require
المطلوبة
to successfully complete a task.
لإكمال المهمة بنجاح
And taking that into the world of climate change --
وعند أخذ ذلك لعالم تغير المناخ،
which is, frankly,
الذي هو بكل صراحة
the Mt. Everest of all problems --
قمة المشكلة لكل المشاكل
just because we've lived the way we have lived for so long,
فقط لأننا عشنا بنفس الطريقة التي عشنا بها لزمن طويل،
just because we have consumed the way we have for so long
فقط لأننا قد أستهلكنا بالطريقة التي أستهلكنا بها لزمن طويل
and populated the earth the way we have for so long,
وعمرنا الأرض بنفس الطريقة لزمن طويل
doesn't mean that we can carry on
لا يعني أننا يمكن أن نواصل
the way we are carrying on.
بنفس الطريقة التي نفعل بها
The warning signs are all there.
إشارات التحذير جميعها هناك
When I was born, the world's population
حينما وُلدت، كان عدد سكان العالم
was 3.5 billion people.
3.5 مليار نسمة
We're now 6.8 billion people,
ونحن الآن 6.8 مليار نسمة
and we're expected to be 9 billion people
ومن المتوقع أن نصل 9 مليارات نسمة
by 2050.
بحلول عام 2050
And then the second lesson,
والدرس الثاني
the radical, tactical shift.
التحوّل الجذري والتكتيكي
And I've come here to ask you today:
وقد حضرت إلى هنا لأطلب منكم اليوم:
what radical tactical shift
ماهي التغيير الجذري التكتيكي
can you take in your relationship to the environment,
يمكنكم أن تفعلوه لعلاقتكم مع البيئة
which will ensure
الذي سيضمن
that our children and our grandchildren
أن أولادنا وأحفادنا
live in a safe world
سيعيشوا في عالم آمن
and a secure world,
وعالم مأمون
and most importantly, in a sustainable world?
والأهم من كل شئ، هل هو عالم مستدام؟
And I ask you, please, to go away from here
وأنا أطلب منكم، رجاءً، لتذهبوا من هنا
and think about that one
وتفكروا حول هذا الشئ
radical tactical shift
التغيير الجذري التكتيكي
which you could make,
الذي يمكنكم فعله
which will make that big difference,
الذي سيحدث الفارق الكبير
and then commit a hundred percent to doing it.
ثم تلتزموا مائة بالمائة بأن تنفذوه
Blog about it, tweet about it, talk about it,
أكتبوا عنه بالتدوين، عبر تويتر، تحدثوا عنه
and commit a hundred percent,
والتزموا مائة بالمائة
because very, very few things
لأن القليل جداً من الأشياء
are impossible to achieve
من المستحيل تحقيقها
if we really put our whole minds to it.
إلا إذا وضعنا كل تركيزنا عليها
So thank you very, very much.
لذا شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)